Finding Aid for the Albert Goldberg Papers PASC-M.0010
UCLA Library Special Collections
Albert Goldberg papers
1908-1986
UCLA Library Special Collections
Goldberg, Albert (Conductor)
PASC-M.0010
8.8 Linear Feet (20 boxes)
This collection holds the scrapbooks, clippings and printed ephemera of conductor and music critic Albert Goldberg. The bulk of the collection consists of his own writing as well as materials about the Works Progress Administration Federal Music Project for which he was the Illinois State Director.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
This collection was originally acquired from Albert Goldberg's estate.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942330843606533
Biography
Albert Levi Goldberg was born on June 2, 1898 in Shenandoah, Iowa. Along with studying music privately, Goldberg attended the University of Nebraska from 1915-1916 and the Chicago Music College from 1920-1922. He received his Masters degree in Music from the Gunn School of Music in 1923. Shortly afterwards, Goldberg started his lengthy career in music review and criticism at the Chicago Herald and Examiner between the years of 1925 and 1936. He then took on the role of Illinois State Director of the Federal Music Project in the Works Progress Administration (WPA) at the beginning of the program in 1935 until the program termination in 1943. He often conducted the orchestras that played within this program. After his experience in the WPA, he continued his music criticism writing for the Chicago Tribune (1943-1947) and the Los Angeles Times (1947-65). Goldberg often lectured in the music department at UCLA beginning in 1948 until the mid 1950s. Goldberg wrote his column The Sounding Board in the Los Angeles Times for 18 years. He became the music staff writer in 1965 and critic emeritus the following year at the Los Angeles Times. He continued to write for other publications after his retirement as well. Goldberg died on February 4, 1990 in Pasadena, CA.
Scope and Content
This collection holds the writings, scrapbooks, clippings and printed ephemera of conductor and music critic Albert Goldberg. The bulk of the collection consists of his own writing as well as materials about the Works Progress Administration Federal Music Project for which he was the Illinois State Director. Other materials include Goldberg's personal collection of sheet music booklets from various classical musicians.
Organization and Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the following series:
Series 1: Personal, 1916-1975
Series 2: Sheet Music, 1908-1976
Series 3: Works Progress Administration Federal Music Project, 1933-1975 (bulk 1933-1943)
Series 4: Writings, 1910-1986
Related Oral History
The following oral history is available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
The Sounding Board [oral history transcript] / Albert Goldberg, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, c1988. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Music critics -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Federal Music Project (U.S.); Goldberg, Albert (Conductor)
- Series 1. Personal, 1916-1975
  Scope and Content
  The personal files of Albert Goldberg include primary materials he collected about Los Angeles' Dorothy Chandler Pavilion, newspaper clippings on his father's death from surgery, articles and flyers featuring Goldberg, and correspondence between friends.
  - The Chicago Symphony Orchestra: Book, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1955-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Dorothy Chandler Pavilion, 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Events, 1930-1934, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Father's Death, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Programs, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publicity, 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series 2. Sheet Music, 1908-1976
  This series is comprised of Albert Goldberg's personal sheet music and opera book collection of various composers. Some of the records in this series pertain to a specific iterance of the score or opera. Some of the production houses involved in these specific renditions were the Chicago Civic Opera Company (Beethoven's Fidelio and Alfano's Resurrection), USC School of Performing Arts (A Midsummer Night's Dream), the Metropolital Opera Association (Wozzeck). Publisher's in this collection include Ernst Eulenburg, John F. Huber, Fred Rullman, Boosey & Hawkes, Westminster Recording Co., Oliver Ditson Company, Ricordi, Edizioni Suvini Zerboni, M. Baron Inc., and Editions Max Eschig. Some of the books have handwritten annotation by Goldberg.
  - Alfano, Frank: Resurrection, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bach, Johann Sebastian: Six Partitas, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bartok, Bela: 3rd Piano Concerto, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bartok, Bela: Sonata for Two Pianos and Percussion, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van: Concerto No. 1 in C major Op. 15, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van: Concerto No. 4 in G major op. 58, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van: Klavier-Trio in B flat major Op. 97, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Beethoven, Ludwig van: Fidelio, 1930, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bizet, Georges: Carmen, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Boito, Arrigo: Mefistofele, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Brahms, Johannes: Piano Concerto No. 1 in D Minor Op. 15, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Brahms, Johannes: Piano Concerto No. 2 in B Flat Major Op. 83, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Britten, Benjamin: A Midsummer Night's Dream, 1960, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Buchner, Georg: Wozzeck, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Catalani, Alfredo: Loreley, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Charpentier, Gustave: Louise, Circa 1920 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cherubini, Luigi: Portuguese Inn, The, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Grieg, Edvard: Piano Concerto in A Minor Op. 16, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Liszt, Franz: Piano Concerto No. 1 in E Flat Major, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Liszt, Franz: Piano Concerto No. 2 in A Major, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Liszt, Franz: Totentanz, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ljadow, Anatoli: The Enchanted Lake Op. 62, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Mozart, Amadeus: Piano Concerto No. 537 in D Major, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mozart, Amadeus: Piano Concerto No. 488 in A Major, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Mozart, Amadeus: Piano Concerto No. 365 for Two Pianos in E Flat Major, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Szymanowski, Karol: Symphony No. 4 Op. 60, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Tschaikowsky, Pyotr Ilyich: Piano Concerto No. 1 in B Flat Minor Op. 23, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Series 3. Works Progress Administration Federal Music Project, 1933-1975 (bulk 1933-1943)
  This series includes correspondence, reports, photographs, clippings, and ephemera. Correspondence documents the progress of the orchestras under Goldberg's supervision; correspondents include composer Frederick A. Stock, New Deal era arts administrator Florence Kerr, the Library of Congress' Chief of Music Division Harold Spivacke, and FWA Director Evelyn S. Byron. Also present is the final report back on the Illinois Music Project in 1943 as well as the official WPA style sheet for typographical uniformity in programming music compositions. Concert programs, flyers and reviews for the various orchestras Goldberg managed and conducted are also found in this series. Photographs included depict Goldberg and his colleagues posing with their orchestras as well as candid shots together. The scrapbook in this collection consists of an arrangement of programs and reviews of concerts. The Works Progress Administration file includes newspaper clippings about Roosevelt putting an end to the WPA.
  The title Illinois Music Project refers to the general WPA program under which Goldberg worked as State Director and conductor. The orchestra initially took on the name Illinois Symphonic Ensemble. The orchestra then adopted the name Illinois Symphony Orchestra which was maintained throughout its existence.
  - Correspondence, 1940-1943 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Illinois Music Project, 1941 March-1943 February (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Illinois Symphonic Ensemble: Large Programs, 1942 June 17 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Illinois Symphonic Ensemble: Small Programs, 1941 May 5-1943 January 14 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Illinois Symphony Orchestra: Large Programs, 1936 August 12-1942 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Illinois Symphony Orchestra: Small Programs, First Season, 1936 October-1937 June (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Illinois Symphony Orchestra: Small Programs, Second Season, October 1937 - June 1938 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Illinois Symphony Orchestra: Small Programs, Third Season, 1938 October-1939 June (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Illinois Symphony Orchestra: Small Programs, Fourth Season, 1939 December-1940 August (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Illinois Symphony Orchestra: Small Programs, Fifth Season, 1940 October-1941 April (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Illinois Symphony Orchestra: Small Programs, Sixth Season, 1941 November-1942 June (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Illinois Symphony Orchestra: Other Programs, 1936 June-1937 November (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Other Federal Music Project Programs, 1933-1936 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1939-1942 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, small, circa 1936-1940s (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Publicity, 1936-1942, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Scrapbook, 1936-1940 (Box 8)
  - Works Progress Administration, 1940-1943 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series 4. Writings, 1910-1986
  This series is mostly newspaper articles written by Albert Goldberg as a music critic for several publications such as The Chicago Herald and Examiner, The Chicago Tribune, The Los Angeles Times, Musical America, Music Digest, and Opera News amongst others. Most of his reviews and critiques are for opera and classical music.
  - Subseries 1. Early drafts, circa 1910s-1927 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2. Clippings, 1910-1986
    Consists of loos newspaper clippings, arranged chronologically. The 1963-1965 folder titled "Los Angeles Times The Sounding Board and Calendar" includes a column titled "The Music Critic Versus the Avant-Garde" to which two follow up articles were written due to the overwhelming written responses Goldberg received after publishing the original article. Goldberg includes a long quote from a letter written by former UCLA faculty member Leonard Stein in which he attacks Goldberg's negative opinion of avant-garde musical compositions.
    - Musical America, 1927-1937, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Music Digest, Chicago Herald and Examiner, 1928-1935 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Chicago Sunday Tribune, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Chicago Tribune, 1944-1947 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1947 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1948 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1949-1956 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1959 - 1960 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board and Calendar, 1963 -1965 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Chicago Sun Times, Opera News, Washington Post, 1965 - 1985 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1966-1968 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Opera News, San Jose Mercury, 1966 - 1968 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1971 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1972 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1973-1976 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1978-1979 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1980-1981 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1983-1984 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Los Angeles Times, undated (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Chicago Tribune, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Other Writers' Clippings, 1930-1985 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 3. Scrapbooks, 1925-1966
    Scrapbooks consist of newspaper articles of Goldberg's and are arranged chronologically. Duplications may exist between articles included in scrapbooks and those that are loose as clippings.
    - Musical America, Music Digest, Herald Examiner, 1925-1931 (Box 12)
    - Chicago Sunday Tribune, 1943-1947 (Box 13)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1947-1954 (Box 14)
    - Guide to arrangement of scrapbook, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1947-1950; This item has been water damaged. (Box 15)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1950-1953 (Box 16)
    - Los Angeles Times, New York Times, Saturday Review, 1953-1956 (Box 16)
    - Los Angeles Times: The Sounding Board, 1956 - 1958 (Box 17)
    - Los Angeles Times, Musical America, Opera News, 1958-1960 (Box 18)
    - Los Angeles Times, The Piano Teacher, Bravo!, Opera News, The School Musician, 1963-1965 (Box 19)
    - Los Angeles Times, Montreal Star, The Union Teacher, Opera News, Pavilion, 1965-1966 (Box 20)
  - Subseries 4. Full publications, 1929-1964 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    Full publications with Goldberg's writing.